Guide to the Ethelbert Nevin Collection, 1834-1980 CAM.NEV.1987.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ethelbert Nevin Collection
1834-1980
1880-1901
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Nevin, Ethelbert
CAM.NEV.1987.01
26 Linear Feet
The collection contains compositions by Ethelbert Nevin (1862-1901), a composer from Sewickley, Pa. In addition to his published songs and unpublished manuscripts, this collection houses correspondence to and from him, photographs of him and his family, press write-ups about him and his works, plus a number of his material possessions.
Arrangement
Items are arranged into twelve different series including Music (published works, manuscripts, and compositions by others), Books, Programs (split up between concerts by Nevin, concerts of his music by others, and other programs), Clippings (divided into concert write-ups, social events, obituaries, and others), Articles about Nevin, Correspondences, Photographs, Business Records, Personal Books, Mementos, Poems, and Furniture.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Biography
Ethelbert Woodbridge Nevin was born in Edgeworth near Sewickley, Pa., in the suburb of Pittsburgh on November 25, 1862, and died in New Haven, CT, at the age of 38 on February 17, 1901. He started his musical lessons with local musicians and published his first composition at the age of 12. In 1878, he attended Western University (now the University of Pittsburgh) but left at the end of his freshman year in 1879. Between 1882-1883 he studied piano with B.J. Lang and composition with Stephen A. Emery in Boston. Between 1884-1886 he went to Berlin to study piano with Karl Klindworth and theory with Otto Tiersch. In December 1886, he gave his professional piano recital debut in Pittsburgh and was enthusiastically received. From 1887 until his death in 1901, he spent most of his life working as a pianist and composer outside of Pittsburgh, living in various places throughout the New England area and in Europe. He was recognized as one of the four major composers in Pennsylvania as well as one of the major American composers. His compositions mostly consisted of songs and piano works, among which the best known works were the short pieces, including "The Rosary," "Mighty Lak'a Rose," and "Narcissus."
Custodial History
The Ethelbert Nevin Collection was acquired by the University of Pittsburgh between 1933 and 1956. The materials were either purchased from or donated by Mrs. Ethelbert Nevin, other family members, and friends. Although Chancellor John Bowman made a public announcement about building the Ethelbert Nevin Memorial Room at the University, the promise was never carried out. Even the proposal to publish an annotated calendar of the Nevin materials by a committee in 1951 and 1952 did not materialize due to the lack of funding. Ruth Crawford Mitchell, then director of the Nationality Rooms at the University, was entrusted with the collection by Chancellor Bowman and had been in charge of the materials until 1959, when she was asked to transfer the collection over to Dr. Theodore Finney, then Chairman of the Music Department. At the time of the transferral, Mitchell compiled a Master List of the Collection, identifying the items and their individual storage location. By about 1960, the transferral to Dr. Finney was completed and the materials, except for the furniture and furnishings, were kept in a safe in Dr. Finney's office. In 1968, Dr. Finney retired. In 1971 the Music Department was moved from the Cathedral of Learning to the present Music Building, and the safe which contained the Collection was placed on the first floor next to the Chairman's Office in the Music Building. By around 1980, the safe was opened and the collection was transferred to Dr. Norris Stephens, Music Librarian of the University, and was kept in two cabinets in the Music Library in the basement of the Music Building. The Collection was transferred again in 1999 and now resides in two file cabinets in the Center for American Music in the University of Pittsburgh's Stephen Foster Memorial.
Scope and Content Notes
The Master List classifies the collection into seven categories: I. Original manuscripts, II. Letters, III. Mementos, IV. Furniture and furnishings, V. Printed matters, VI. Special gifts, and VII. Materials not in possession of the University. The items within each category are mostly arranged by who and when the items were presented; in other words, items presented by one person on a certain date were listed together. Because of such arrangements, sometimes items are listed under inappropriate categories, like letters included under mementos, or printed scores kept under manuscripts. Sometimes items are duplicated in more than one category. In addition, the desciption of each item is often rather vague, without dimensions or other details. This often creates problems when one tries to identify a certain item in the List with its corresponding material in the Collection. This problem occurs most frequently in the categories of personal mementos and "special gifts." Moreover, some items are mentioned collectively without individual entry. For example, about three hundred letters were listed under one general entry: "general collection of letters written by Ethelbert Nevin." This also happens with the clippings and programs. Under such circumstances, we cannot check which items are missing.
Music; Sewickley (Pa.); Composers -- Pittsburgh, Pa.; University of Pittsburgh; Composers -- United States; Popular music -- United States -- 1901-1910; Music -- Manuscripts; Nevin, Ethelbert; Nevin, Robert Peebles; Nevin, Anne Paul; Cather, Willa
- Music, 1881-1903; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The series is divided into three subseries: Published Works by Nevin, Manuscripts by Nevin, and Compositions by Others. Published works by Nevin is divided into four sections: songs, piano works, choral works, and instrumental works. Manuscripts by Nevin is divided into five sections: songs, piano works, chorus, instrumental works, and other manuscripts. Other manuscripts are described at the item level. Works with opus numbers precede those without opus numbers. Opus numbered works are arranged by numerical order while pieces without opus numbers are arranged alphabetically. If there is no instance summary for an item it is presumed missing.
  - Published works by Nevin, 1.
    Major keys are described in uppercase letters. Minor keys are described in lowercase letters.
    - Songs, A.
      - A Sketchbook: a group of songs and piano pieces, 1888 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 1)
        A Sketchbook: a group of songs and piano pieces. Boston: Boston Music, 1888. 28 cm
        Contents: No. 1 Gavotte, for piano [in g], [2] p., [dedicated] to E.F.B. No. 2 Im wunderschönen Monat Mai/ Text: Heine, with Eng. Trans., for soprano or tenor and piano [in G flat], [2] p., [dedicated] to E.F. No. 3 Love song, for piano [in A], [2] p., [dedicated] to W.C.S. No. 4 Du bist wie eine Blume/ Text: Heine, with Eng. Trans., for soprano or tenor and piano [in G], [2] p., [dedicated] to E.D.N. No. 5. Berceuse, for piano [in A flat], [1] p., [dedicated] to C.W.S. No. 6 Lehn deine Wang' an meine Wang'/ Heine, with Eng. Trans., for soprano or tenor and piano [in G flat', [2] p., [dedicated] to E.S.P. No. 7 Serenata, for piano [in a], [3] p., [dedicated] to P.R.O No. 8 Oh! That we two were maying/ Text: Kingsley, for soprano or tenor and piano [in A flat], [4] p., [dedicated to A.P.N No. 9 Valse rhapsodie, for piano [in C], [3] p., [dedicated] to P.C.O. No. 10 Three songs from "A child's garden of Verse"/ Text by R.L. Stevenson, for voice and piano no. 1 "In winter I got up at night," [in G] [2] p., [dedicated to J.R.Mc.A no. 2 "Of speckled eggs, the birdie sings", [in E], [1] p., [dedicated] to E.F.H. no. 3 "Dark-brown is the river", [in G flat], [4] p., dedicated to M.F.A. No. 11 The night has a thousand eyes/ text: Bourdillon, for mixed voice quartet with violin obligato [in F], [2] p., [dedicated] to W.I.N. Op 2.
      - A Sketchbook: a group of songs and piano pieces, 1888 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 2)
      - A Sketchbook: a group of songs and piano pieces, 1888 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 3)
        A sketchbook: a group of song and piano pieces. Boston: Boston Music, 1888 28 cm.
        Contents: No 1. Gavotte, for piano [in g], [2] p., [dedicated] to E.F.B. No 2. Im wunderschönen Monat Mai/ Text: Heine, with Engl. Trans., for soprano or tenor and piano [in G flat], [2] p., [dedicated] to E.F. No. 3 Love song,for piano [in A], [2] p., [dedicated] to W.C.S. No. 4 Du bist wie eine Blume/ Text: Heine, with Eng. Trans., for soprano or tenor and piano [in G], [2] p., [dedicated] to E.D.N. No. 5. Berceuse, for piano [in A flat], [1] p., [dedicated] to C.W.S. No. 6 Lehn deine Wang' an meine Wang'/ Heine, with Eng. Trans., for soprano or tenor and piano [in G flat', [2] p., [dedicated] to E.S.P. No. 7 Serenata, for piano [in a], [3] p., [dedicated] to P.R.O No. 8 Oh! That we two were maying/ Text: Kingsley, for soprano or tenor and piano [in A flat], [4] p., [dedicated] to A.P.N No. 9 Valse rhapsodie, for piano [in C], [3] p., [dedicated] to P.C.O. No. 10 Three songs from "A child's garden of Verse"/ Text by R.L. Stevenson, for voice and piano no. 1 "In winter I got up at night," [in G] [2] p., [dedicated to J.R.Mc.A no. 2 "Of speckled eggs, the birdie sings", [in E], [1] p., [dedicated] to E.F.H. no. 3 "Dark-brown is the river", [in G flat], [4] p., dedicated to M.F.A. No. 11 The night has a thousand eyes/ text: Bourdillon, for mixed voice quartet with violin obligato [in F], [2] p., [dedicated] to W.I.N. Op 2. Inscribed on cover: Annchen from Bert, Quincy, Jan. 20, 1898, First sketch book.
      - Herbstefühl (Autumn Sadness)/Text: Karl Gerok, with Eng. trans., 1889 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 4)
        Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([2] p.); 35 cm. For voice and piano [in A flat]. [Dedicated] to Fraulein Clothilde von Finck. Op. 5, no. 1
      - Little Boy Blue/Text: Eugene Field, 1891 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 5)
        Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([4] p.); 35 cm. For soprano and tenor and piano [in B flat]. [Dedicated] to W.S.O. Op. 12, no. 4
      - A Book of Songs, 1893 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 6)
        A Book of Songs Boston: Boston Music, 1893 30 cm. For voice and piano
        Contents: No. 1 "A Fair Good Morn"/Text: [not credited] (Manchester, 1893) [in E flat], [3] p., [dedicated] To my Mother. No. 2 "Sleep, Little Tulip"/Text: Eugene Field (Manchester, 1893) [in A flat], [5] p. No. 3 "Ev'ry Night" (A song for little boys)/ Text: R.L. Stevenson [in F], [1] p. No. 4 "Airly Beacon"/Text: Rev'd Chas. Kingsley (Quincy, 1889) [in E flat], [2] p. No. 5 "When the land was white with Moonlight"/Text: Anna Reeve Aldrich (Manchester 1893) [in E], [3] p. No. 6 A song of Love/Text: Edmond Lock Tomlin (Paris, 1891) [in E flat], [2] p. No. 7 Nocturne/Text: T.B. Algrich (Quasi, Fla. 18930 [in F], [4] p. No. 8 Dites-Moi/English Text: Mrs. O. Boise (Manchester, 1893) [in E flat], [2] p. No. 9 Orsola's Song Chantez! La nuit sera breve/Text Richepin (Paris, 18920 [in f sharp], [4] p. No. 10 In der Nacht (In the Night)/Text: Graf platen (Berlin, 1892) [in g], [5] p. Op. 20 2 copies.
        1 copy bad.
      - A Book of Songs, 1893 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 7)
        Boston: Boston Music. 30 cm. For voice and piano
        Contents: No. 1 "A Fair Good Morn"/Text: [not credited] (Manchester, 1893) [in E flat], [3] p., [dedicated] To my Mother. No. 2 "Sleep, Little Tulip"/Text: Eugene Field (Manchester, 1893) [in A flat], [5] p. No. 3 "Ev'ry Night" (A song for little boys)/ Text: R.L. Stevenson [in F], [1] p. No. 4 "Airly Beacon"/Text: Rev'd Chas. Kingsley (Quincy, 1889) [in E flat], [2] p. No. 5 "When the land was white with Moonlight"/Text: Anna Reeve Aldrich (Manchester 1893) [in E], [3] p. No. 6 A song of Love/Text: Edmond Lock Tomlin (Paris, 1891) [in E flat], [2] p. No. 7 Nocturne/Text: T.B. Algrich (Quasi, Fla. 18930 [in F], [4] p. No. 8 Dites-Moi/English Text: Mrs. O. Boise (Manchester, 1893) [in E flat], [2] p. No. 9 Orsola's Song Chantez! La nuit sera breve/Text Richepin (Paris, 18920 [in f sharp], [4] p. No. 10 In der Nacht (In the Night)/Text: Graf von Platen (Berlin, 1892) [in g], [5] p. Op. 20. Inscribed on cover: This is my first copy of "A Book of Song" Belong to my dear wife Anne Nevin, Dec. 1893 CHECK
      - Rechte Zeit (Time enough)/Text: Julius Stinde from "Der Liedermacher", 1896 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 8)
        Eng. Trans: by Th. Baker Boston: Boston Music, 1896 1 score ([2] p.); 35 cm. For voice and piano [in A flat] Op. 22, no 1. Lyrics by Julius Stinde; also a page with German words. Poor condition.
      - At Rest/Text by Frank L. Stanton, 1901 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 9)
        At Rest/Text by Frank L. Stanton Cincinnati: John Church, 1901 1 score ([2] p.); 33 cm. For voice and piano [in G] Inscribed on cover: Anne Paul Nevin, First copy, Autumn 1901.
      - A Bed Time Song/Text: Lillian Dynevor Rice, 1887 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 10)
        Boston: Oliver Ditson. 1 score ([3] p.); 36 cm. For voice and piano [in A flat]. On cover: Boston, Oct. 22, 1887 First edition.
      - The Rosary, A Life Lesson/Text: Robert Cameron Rodgers, 1898 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 11)
        First edition. Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([3] p.); 35 cm. For voice and piano. On cover: To Elizabeth Dickson with gratitude and warm affection from Ethelbert Nevin, Vinacre, July 1898.
      - The Lovers/Words by Clark W. Bryan; music by "Woodbridge", 1881 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 12)
        First Edition Cincinnati: John Church 1 score ([7] p.); 36 cm. [Dedicated] to Miss Bessie Fleming, Sewickley, Pa.
      - Mighty Lak' a Rose/Text by Frank L. Stanton, 1901 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 13)
        Cincinnati: John Church. 1 score ([2] p.); 33 cm. For low voice and piano. [Dedicated] to Mrs. Adele Laeis Baldwin Extremely fragile condition.
      - Mighty Lak' a Rose/Text by Frank L. Stanton, 1901 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 14)
        For Medium Voice in G. Theodore Presser Co. The John Church Division, 1712 Chestnut Street, Philadelphia, PA. In pencil on cover page: Adam never had no mammy - Mrs. Brennan. Elsie Brese Mitchell, 4.
      - O! For a Closer Walk with God/Text: William Gowper; sacred words adapted by Oliver Creed and edited by H. Cough-Leighter [?], 1900 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 15)
        Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([6] p.); 34 cm. For voice and piano. Adaptation of "The Rosary" to sacred words. Edits in red pencil.
      - The Rosary - Le Chapelet - Der Rosenkranz/Text by Robert Cameron Rodgers; French version by Isadore Martinez; German Version by Dr. Th. Baker, 1900 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 16)
        Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([3] p.); 33 cm. For mezzo-soprano or baritone and piano [in D flat]. Cover seems to belong to a different copy of this piece listing the voice and key as "soprano or baritone and piano [in E flat]"
      - The Rosary - Le Rosaire - Der Rosenkranz; French translation by Mme. C. Eschig, German by Carl Engel, 1898 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 17)
        The Rosary, Le Rosaire, Der Rosenkranz / Text: Robert Cameron Rogers French version by Mme. C. Eschig, German version by Carl Engel Boston: Boston Music, 1898 1 score ([3] p.); 33 cm. For Mezzo Soprano or baritone and piano [in D flat] Cover does not seem to match and lists voice and key as soprano or tenor [in D flat]
      - The Rosary - Le Rosaire - Der Rosenkranz French traslation by Mme. C. Eshcig; German translation by Carl Engel, 1898 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 18)
        For Soprano or Tenor in D Flat English, French & German Words The Boston Music Company, (5p)
      - Le Rosaire (The Rosary)/Text: Robert Cameron Rodgers; French trans. Amedee Boutarel, 1898 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 19)
        Paris: Edition Costallat, [19?]. 1 score ([2] p.); 35 cm. For voice and piano [in F]. Voice part written on separate sized insert. ([2] p.); 28 cm.
      - Le Rosaire (The Rosary)/ Text: Robert Cameron Rodgers; French trans. Amedee Boutarel, 1913 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 20)
        Paris: Edition Costallat, [19??] 1 score ([1] p.); 28 cm. For voice and piano [in C]. stamped "specimen."
      - The Rosary (in Russian), 1898 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 21)
        Leipzig: C.G. Roder, G M. B. H., [19??]. 1 score ([3] p.); 34 cm. Russian and English Texts. For voice and piano [in D flat].
      - Der Rosenkranz (The Rosary) (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 22)
        Leipzig: Friedrich Hofmeister, reprint. 1 score ([3] p.); 34 cm. German trans. written in pencil above each system and in red ink, replacing the original Eng. text. For soprano or tenor and piano [in E flat].
      - Serenade (Good-night! Good-night beloved)/Text: Longfellow, 1884 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 23)
        Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([4] p.); 35 cm. For soprano and piano [in B]. [Dedicated] to Miss Marge G. Irwin, Edgeworth. On cover: Anne Paul Nevin - faithfully yours, Ethelbert Nevin, Vineacre 1875. First Edition
      - Stars of the Summer Night/Text: Henry W. Longfellow, 1887 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 24)
        Boston: Oliver Ditson. 1 score ([3] p.); 36 cm. For voice and piano [in E]. [Dedicated] to Miss Anne Paul. First edition.
      - Summer Longings/Text: Dennis F. MacCarthy, 1887 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 25)
        Boston: Oliver Ditson. 1 score ([3] p.); 36 cm. For voice and piano. First edition.
      - When All the World is Young, Lad/Text: Charles Kingsley, 1883 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 26)
        Boston: Oliver Ditson. 1 score ([3] p.); 29 cm. For voice and piano [in A].
    - Piano Works, 1890-1929; B.
      - In Arcady, 1892 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 26)
        Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([25] p.); 30 cm. For piano. 2 copies.
      - May in Tuscany (Maggio in Toscana), 1895 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 27)
        Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([29] p.).; 29 cm. For piano. On cover inscribed: Anne Paul Nevin, Sept. 13, 1899. Op. 21.
      - Barchetta, 1896 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 28)
        Melbourne: Allan & Co., reprint. 1 score ([3] p.); 31 cm. For piano. Op. 21, no. 3.
      - Un Giorno in Venezia (A Day in Venice), 1898 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 29)
        Cincinnati: John Church. 29 cm. Contents: No. 1 Alba (Dawn) [in F] ([3] p.) - Missing. No. 2 Gondolieri (Gondoliers )[in E] ([5] p.) No. 3 Canzone Amorosa (Venetian Love Song) [in A flat] ([3] p.) No. 4 Buona Notte (Good Night) [in A flat] ([4] p.) - Missing. Op. 25
      - Un Giorno in Venezia (A Day in Venice), 1898 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 30)
        Cincinnati: John Church. 29 cm. With Illustrations Contents: No. 1 Alba (Dawn) [in F] ([3] p.). No. 2 Gondolieri (Gondoliers )[in E] ([5] p.) No. 3 Canzone Amorosa (Venetian Love Song) [in A flat] ([3] p.) No. 4 Buona Notte (Good Night) [in A flat] ([4] p.). Op. 25
      - Un Giorno in Venezia (A Day in Venice) for Piano, 1899 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 31)
        Cincinnati: John Church. 29 cm. With Illustrations Contents: No. 1 Alba (Dawn) [in F] ([3] p.). No. 2 Gondolieri (Gondoliers )[in E] ([5] p.) No. 3 Canzone Amorosa (Venetian Love Song) [in A flat] ([3] p.) No. 4 Buona Notte (Good Night) [in A flat] ([4] p.). Op. 25. Poor Condition.
      - Captive Memories: A Suite for Piano, 1929 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 32)
        Captive Memories: A Suite for Piano 1 score ([16] p.); 29 cm. Bound work, printed. 2 copies.
        Contents: [No. 1] Arcady [in F]. ([2] p.) [No. 2] Admiration [in C]. ([3] p.) [No. 3] Enchantment and Devotion [in E flat]. ([4] p.) [No. 4] Serenade [in E flat]. ([5] p.) [No. 5] Aspiration [in G flat]. ([3] p.) Op. 29.
      - A June Night in Washington, 1899 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 33)
        Cincinnati: John Church, 1899; Theodore Presser Co. (1930). 1 score ([9] p.); 31 cm. On cover: Souvenir edition for the Washington Bicentennial. For piano. Op. 30, no. 4.
      - Der Rosenkranz, 1905 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 34)
        Berlin: E. D. Bote & G. Bock. 1 score ([3] p.); 34 cm. For piano [in D flat]. 2 copies.
      - Narcissus - hard cover, 1899 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 35)
        Narcissus / Arr. by A. Moffat, Text by Gustav Strube Boston: Boston Music, 1899 1 score ([4] p.); 32 cm. For violin and piano [in A flat] On t.p.: inscribed to Theodore M. Finney, (illegible cursive) 1920 Op. 13 no. 4
      - Narcissus, 1899 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 36)
        Narcissus Boston: Boston Music, 1899. 1 score ([5] p.); 32 cm. For piano - two hands [in A flat]. On t.p.: "Inez F. Patterson" 2 copies
      - Narcissus - archivally bound, 1891 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 37)
        Narcissus Boston: Boston Music, 1891 and 1899 1 score ([5] p.); 32 cm. For piano [in A flat]. Op. 13 no. 4
    - Chorus, 1880-1903; C.
      - Captive Memories: a Song Cycle for Baritone with quartet of mixed voices, recitative, and piano accompaniment/Text: James T. White, 1899 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 38)
        Captive Memories: A Song Cycle for Baritone with Quartet of Mixed Voices, Recitative, and Piano Accompaniment / Text: James T. White. Cincinnati: John Church, 1899. 1 score ([36] p.); 29 cm.
        Contents: Prelude: Love is the Way to Arcady [in F]. ([5] p.) Admiration [in C]. ([4] p.) Enchantment: The Touch of her dear Hand [in E]. ([1] p.) Devotion [in B flat]. ([1] p.) Aspiration [in G flat]. ([2] p.) In the soft still night [in c]. ([7] p.) Entreaty [in D]. ([6] p.) Marriage [in D]. ([9] p.)
        On the t.p.: "To my dear M---? with a happy Christmas from Doris—the very first copy. ---Ethelbert Nevin, Dec., 1899." Op. 29.
      - A Christmas Hymn/Text: Edwin Ford, 1937 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 39)
        Cincinnati: John Church. 1 score ([1] p.); 27 cm. For chorus a capella. In caption: Published for the Centennial Celebration of the Sewickley Presbyterian Church, Sewickley, PA. At end: The original manuscript of this herefore unpublished hymn was presented by Mrs. Ethelbert Nevin to the University of Pittsburgh Ethelbert Nevin Memorial Room Collection.
      - The Passion (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 40)
        A flat In the Plymouth Hymnal. 1 p.; 22 cm. For SATB chorus.
      - The Rosary, 1900 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 41)
        Published by G. Schirmer Jr. for all countries. For mixed voices (SATB) with piano accompaniment. In The Plymouth Hymnal ed. Lyman Abbott, No. 189. [1] p.; 22 cm. For chorus.
        *newer acquisition not included in first two original finding aids*
      - Jubilate Deo, 1890 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 42)
        G. Shirmer. Boston: Boston Music. 1 score ([5] p.); 27 cm. For mixed voice chorus and organ [in B flat]. Op. 11, no. 2.
      - The Land of Heart's Desire (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 43)
        Land of Heart's Desire - Cantata for Women's Voices - from The Quest / Arr. by Deems Taylor, text by Randolph Hartley Cincinnati: The John Church Company 1 score ([90] p.); 29 cm. For baritone solo and three-part chorus of women's voices On t.p.: written in pencil "Alice Murray"
    - Instrumental Works, D.
      - The Rosary/Arr. by Gustav Strube; transcribed for violin or cello and piano, 1903 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 44)
        The Rosary/Arr. By Gustav Strube; transcribed for violin or cello and piano. Melbourne: Allan & Co., [19?]. 1 score ([3] p.); 32 cm. For violin or cello and piano [in D flat]. On t.p.: Also published in simplified edition by P. Th. Miersch in the key of D.
      - Narcissus, 1925 (File-cabinet 18, Drawer 3, Folder 45)